Guide to the Mary McMillan papers, 1936-1997 and undated, bulk 1952-1991 RL.00881
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mary McMillan papers
1936-1997 and undated, bulk 1952-1991
1952-1991
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McMillan, Mary, 1912-
RL.00881
8.1 Linear Feet 13 manuscript boxes; 2 oversize boxes; 2 oversize folders
2277 Items
Collection Overview
The Mary McMillan Papers, 1936-1997 and undated (bulk 1952-1991), consist chiefly of journals and printed material, but also include correspondence, writings and speeches, photographic material, scrapbooks, clippings, videocassettes, audio cassettes, and memorabilia. Arranged in nine series based primarily on the format of the material, the papers illuminate the personal life and professional work of McMillan, a United Methodist missionary and teacher at the Hiroshima Jo Gakuin College in Hiroshima, Japan. In addition to her work as a teacher, the collection documents McMillan's service to the Kyodan, a unifying organization for Christian missionaries in Japan, and to the hibakusha, the survivors of the atomic bomb attacks on Hiroshima and Nagasaki, as well as her peace activism. Also included are materials related to the Topaz Relocation Center, a Japanese-American internment camp in Utah where McMillan worked in 1943. The papers are mostly in English, but include some Japanese language materials.
The bulk of the collection consists of the Journals Series, whose 43 journals contain almost daily accounts of McMillan's work at Hiroshima Jo Gakuin College, her involvement with the Ushita Christian Church, and her encounters with friends and other people. Also included are her personal thoughts about world events, particularly those related to peace and nuclear disarmament. Beginning on Aug. 11, 1939 with the final preparations for her initial departure, McMillan records her activities through her first year and a half in Japan. The 1939 and 1940 journals document in depth McMillan's adaptation to life in Japan, including her training in the Japanese language and customs, her first visits to various cities throughout the country, and the difficulties she faced as an American woman in pre-World War II Japan. After she and other American workers in Hiroshima were forcibly evacuated on Feb. 29, 1941, journal entries are scarce; however, the almost-daily entries resume in 1952 and continue until the day of McMillan's death on July 19, 1991.
In addition to the journals, McMillan's professional work as a United Methodist missionary and teacher at Hiroshima Jo Gakuin College is well documented through the Correspondence Series, Writings and Speeches Series, and Printed Material Series. The Biographical Material Series includes McMillan's handwritten autobiographical notes, as well as newspaper and magazine clippings and booklets documenting McMillan's work at Hiroshima Jo Gakuin College, and with the Ushita Christian Church, which McMillan helped found in 1948. McMillan's correspondence also sheds light on her work through "mission letters," mass mailings which she wrote periodically as a way of updating her supporters in the United States on her work in Hiroshima.
McMillan also was a staunch advocate of world peace and nuclear disarmament, and after her retirement from the United Methodist Church in 1980, she spent much of her time writing letters and speaking in churches throughout the United States promoting her cause. McMillan's role as a pacifist is well well documented throughout the entire collection by her correspondence, photographs of demonstrations and marches, printed materials, and items in the Clippings Series. Much of the material in the Writings and Speeches Series and the Printed Material Series is related to peace activism, and covers topics such as the lingering effects of the atomic bomb attack on Hiroshima and that city's fight for peace, the first-hand accounts of bomb survivors, and the United Methodist Church's pacifist stance.
Also contributing to an understanding of McMillan's life, the Photographic Material Series and the Memorabilia Series offer visual and three-dimensional documentation of her activities as a missionary, teacher, and friend to the Japanese.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1912 Nov. 26 Born, Pensacola, Fla.
1934 Graduated from Florida State College for Women with a degree in literature and history
1934-1937 Taught in Northwest Florida high schools
1939 Graduated from Scarritt College in Nashville with a Masters degree in Christian Education
1939 Aug. 31 Arrived in Japan
1941 Feb. 29 Forced to return to the United States
1942 Took courses in Japanese language at the University of California, Berkeley, and lived in the International House
1943 Taught at the Topaz Relocation Center in Topaz, Utah
1944 Graduated from the Nashville School of Social Work with a Masters in Social Science
1945 Served as a child welfare worker in Escambia County, Fla.
1947 Jan. 7 Became the first Protestant missionary to return to Hiroshima after World War II
1948 Jan. 19 Held the first service of the Ushita Christian Church in her home
1952 Dec. Mother died
1980 Named the sixth Special Honorary Citizen of Hiroshima Named Professor Emerita at Hiroshima Jo Gakuin College
1980 May 26 Left Hiroshima for a six-month furlough prior to her official retirement
1980 Dec. 1 Officially retired from service
1984 Aug. Returned to Hiroshima as a special guest of the city and took part in the memorial ceremony at Peace Park
1991 July 19 Died in Lake Chautauqua, N.Y., at a missionary's conference
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Mary McMillan Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1997.
Japan -- Church history -- 20th century; Japan; Peace -- Religious aspects -- Methodist Church; Nuclear warfare -- Religious aspects -- Methodist Church; Nuclear disarmament; Antinuclear movement; Audiocassettes; Atomic bomb -- Japan -- Hiroshima-shi; Diaries; Atomic bomb -- Moral and ethical aspects; Atomic bomb -- Religious aspects; Videocassettes; Atomic bomb victims -- Japan -- Hiroshima-shi; Women -- Education -- Japan -- 20th century; Women -- Japan -- Social customs; Hiroshima-shi (Japan) -- History; Hiroshima-shi (Japan) -- Description and travel; Peace movements -- Japan; Peace movements -- United States; Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation -- 1942-1945; Missionaries -- Correspondence; Methodist Church -- Japan; Pacifists -- Japan; Pacifists -- United States; Japan -- Social life and customs; World War, 1939-1945 -- Japan -- Personal narratives; Color photographs; Missionaries -- Japan; Women missionaries -- Japan; Black-and-white photographs; Slides (photographs); Scrapbooks; Nihon Kirisuto Kyodan; McMillan, Mary, 1912-; Hiroshima Jo Gakuin College
- Biographical Material Series, 1938-1992 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains biographical material related to Mary McMillan and her work. Included are autobiographical writings, personal and work-related papers, newspaper and magazine clippings, and printed materials documenting her life. Arranged in chronological order.
  - Autobiography and Autobiographical Notes Subseries, 1980-1981, undated
    - 1980 Sept., In Retrospect: My Life as a Teacher, Part I (Box 1)
    - 1981 Sept., In Retrospect: My Life as a Teacher, Part II (Box 1)
    - undated, Mary's Memoirs - Post World War II (Box 1)
    - undated Reflections, 1939-1980 (Box 1)
  - Personal Papers Subseries, 1938-1992 (Box 1)
  - Work-related papers, 1943-1963 (Box 1)
  - Printed Materials Subseries, 1980-1992, undated
    - 1980 Mar., Mary McMillan (in Japanese) (Box 1)
    - 1991 Aug. 11, The Methodist Witness, Vol. 93, No. 32, published by the Pensacola First United Methodist Church (Box 1)
    - 1991 Sept. 29, The Methodist Witness, Vol. 100, No. 39, published by the Pensacola First United Methodist Church (Box 1)
    - 1992 Apr., Mary McMillan and Japan: A Salute and a Tribute, published by the Pensacola First United Methodist Church (Box 1)
    - 1992 July 19,Ushita Church Memorial Service bulletin (Box 1)
    - undated, Hiroshima No Kodama Ni: Mary McMillan (in Japanese) (Box 1)
  - Clippings Subseries, 1949-1992, undated (Box 1)
- Journals Series, 1939-1991
  Contains 43 journals maintained by McMillan during her time in Hiroshima and her retirement, documenting in great detail her daily life and work as well as her travels throughout East Asia. She also noted her thoughts and concerns about world events and her peace activism. Many entries describe visits by her students and friends in Japan and provide a revealing look at Japanese social life and customs. The journals are arranged chronologically. Many small groups of loose materials were found laid into the beginning or end of the journals; these were removed and placed in a separate folder following the journal; some of these items appear to be unrelated to the journals in which they were found.
  - 1939
    - Journal (Box 1)
    - Material removed from 1939 journal (Box 1)
  - 1940
    - Journal (Box 2)
    - Material removed from 1940 journal (Box 2)
  - 1952
    - Journal (Box 2)
    - Material removed from 1952 journal (Box 2)
  - 1953
    - Journal (Box 2)
  - 1954
    - Journal (Box 2)
  - 1955
    - Journal (Box 2)
    - Material removed from 1955 journal (Box 2)
  - 1956
    - Journal (Box 2)
    - Material removed from 1956 journal (Box 2)
    - Journal, 1956 Apr. 6-1956 Apr. 11 (Box 2)
  - 1957
    - Journal (Box 3)
  - 1958
    - Journal (Box 3)
  - 1959
    - Journal (Box 3)
  - 1960
    - Journal (Box 3)
  - 1961
    - Journal (Box 3)
    - Material removed from 1961 journal (Box 3)
  - 1962
    - Journal (Box 3)
    - Material removed from 1962 journal (Box 3)
  - 1963
    - Journal (Box 4)
    - Material removed from 1963 journal (Box 4)
  - 1964
    - Journal (Box 4)
  - 1965
    - Journal (Box 4)
    - Material removed from 1965 journal (Box 4)
  - 1966
    - Journal (Box 4)
    - Material removed from 1966 journal (Box 4)
  - 1967
    - Journal (Box 4)
    - Journal, 1967 Dec. 9-1967 Dec. 31 (Box 4)
  - 1968
    - Journal (Box 4)
  - 1969
    - Journal (Box 5)
    - Material removed from 1969 journal (Box 5)
  - 1970
    - Journal (Box 5)
    - Material removed from 1970 journal (Box 5)
  - 1971
    - Journal (Box 5)
    - Material removed from 1971 journal (Box 5)
  - 1972
    - Journal (Box 5)
    - Material removed from 1972 journal (Box 5)
  - 1973
    - Journal (Box 5)
    - Material removed from 1973 journal (Box 5)
  - 1974
    - Journal (Box 6)
    - Material removed from 1974 journal (Box 6)
  - 1975
    - Journal (Box 6)
    - Material removed from 1975 journal (Box 6)
  - 1976
    - Journal (Box 6)
    - Material removed from 1976 journal (Box 6)
  - 1977-1979
    - Journal (Box 6)
    - Material removed from 1977-1979 journal (Box 6)
  - 1980-1981
    - Journal (Box 6)
    - Material removed from 1980-1981 journal (Box 6)
    - Journal, 1980 June 6-1980 July 21 (Box 7)
  - 1981
    - Journal (Box 7)
    - Material removed from 1981 journal (Box 7)
  - 1982
    - Journal (Box 7)
    - Material removed from 1982 journal (Box 7)
  - 1983
    - Journal (Box 7)
    - Material removed from 1983 journal (Box 7)
  - 1984
    - Journal (Box 7)
    - Material removed from 1984 journal (Box 7)
  - 1985
    - Journal, 1985 Jan. 1-1985 Sept. 7 (Box 7)
    - Journal, 1985 Sept. 8-1985 Dec. 31 (Box 7)
    - Material removed from 1985 Sept. 8-1985 Dec. 31 journal (Box 7)
  - 1986
    - Journal (Box 8)
    - Material removed from 1986 journal (Box 8)
  - 1987
    - Journal (Box 8)
    - Material removed from 1987 journal (Box 8)
  - 1988
    - Journal (Box 8)
    - Material removed from 1988 journal (Box 8)
  - 1990
    - Journal (Box 8)
    - Material removed from 1990 journal (Box 8)
  - 1991
    - Journal (Box 8)
    - Material removed from 1991 journal (Box 8)
- Correspondence Series, 1948-1997 and undated
  Personal and professional correspondence of Mary McMillan, divided into outgoing and incoming subseries and arranged in chronological order. The Outgoing Correspondence primarily contains letters sent by McMillan to churches or individuals in the United States who had supported her work in Japan. These "mission letters" describe McMillan's work at Hiroshima Jo Gakuin College and Ushita Christian Church as well as her beliefs in world peace and disarmament. Some of the Incoming Correspondence, particularly in the early 1980s, is in Japanese. The majority of the letters are to McMillan from friends, missionaries, and former students in Japan after her retirement in 1980. Also included in a small third subseries is other correspondence that was neither to nor from McMillan. Many of these letters were written to Jane Greenwood, McMillan's sister, from individuals and organizations expressing their condolences over McMillan's death. A few pieces of correspondence have photographs clipped to them.
  - Outgoing Correspondence Subseries, 1948-1990 and undated
    - 1948-1990 (Box 9)
    - undated (Box 9)
  - Incoming Correspondence Subseries, 1949-1991 and undated
    - 1949-1979, 1 folder (Box 9)
    - 1980-1991 and undated, 13 folders (Box 9)
  - Other Correspondence Subseries, 1958-1997 and undated (Box 9)
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1958-1993 and undated
  Reports, essays, and other unpublished material, divided into three subseries containing writings by Mary McMillan, writings by other individuals, and audiovisual materials. All items are ordered chronologically within the subseries. The BetaMax and VHS video cassettes in the audiovisual materials subseries require use copies; the audio cassettes have use copies already available.
  - Writings By Mary McMillan Subseries, 1959-1988 and undated
    Primarily handwritten and personal essays documenting peace activism and the nuclear disarmament movements in the United States and Japan.
    - 1959, An Appraisal of my Participation in the Conference against A and H Bombs (Box 10)
    - 1959 Sept., Some Rambling Thoughts After a Spring and Summer Busy with Peace Activities (Box 10)
    - 1981, Hiroshima and Nagasaki Days (Box 10)
    - 1981, Peace (Box 10)
    - 1984, Reflections upon my Recent Return to Hiroshima (Box 10)
    - 1984 Aug., A Journey of and for Mutual Encouragement (Box 10)
    - 1988 Oct. 9, Let There be Peace (Box 10)
    - undated, At This, my First Advent - Christmas Season (Box 10)
    - undated, Hiroshima Jo Gakuin College essay (Box 10)
    - undated, On June 28, 1984 (Box 10)
    - undated, Recent State of Anti-Nuclear Movements in the United States (Box 10)
    - undated, To "Voice of the People" (Box 10)
    - undated, [Handwritten notes] (Box 10)
  - Writings By Others Subseries, 1959-1993 and undated
    Contains reports and essays documenting the peace movement, as well as the growth of the Christian Church in Japan and the works of the Kyodan, the organization which unified the missionaries of the various Protestant denominations in Japan. Also included are poems and other creative works written by McMillan's friends that explore peace and Church activism, as well as tributes to McMillan.
    - 1958 Nov., Radiation and Human Welfare: Why Japan Objects to Nuclear Weapons Testing, Fusa Asaka (Box 10)
    - 1959 Aug. 1, General Report to the Preliminary Session of the 5th World Conference Against Atomic and Hydrogen Bombs, Professor Kaoru Yasui (Box 10)
    - 1959 Aug. 7, The Movement Against A and H Bombs in the Cultural Sphere in Hiroshima, Koichiro Tanabe (Box 10)
    - 1959 Aug. 7, The Report in Literature and the Problem of Peace, no author (Box 10)
    - 1959 Aug. 1-1959 Aug. 8, Fifth World Conference against A and H Bombs: A Survey of the Conference Itself, the Christian Participation and Suggestions for Further Participation, by a group of foreign Christians who reside in Hiroshima and who participated in the 5th conference (Box 10)
    - 1966 Oct. 15, Movements of the Kyodan Interpreted, Kazo Kitamori (Box 10)
    - 1969 Jan. 1, Statistics of Kirisutokyo Nenkan 1969, no author (Box 10)
    - [1969?], Toward a Reconciled Humanity, no author (Box 10)
    - 1969 Dec. 6, A Response to the Reports of the Black Staff Task Force and the Youth, Arthur Gamblin, Mark Reames, Ruth Sarto, and Randolph Thrasher (Box 10)
    - 1970, A Dramalogue for the 25th Year of the Nuclear Age, no author (Box 10)
    - 1971, Kuala Lumpur Report, Jack Hasegawa (Box 10)
    - 1971 Jan., What is Going to Happen to our Kyodan?, Kiyoshi Ii, Takeshi Takasaki, and Yoichi Harada (Box 10)
    - 1971 Feb. 22-1971 Feb. 23, Magazine Overview, Yoshikazo Sakamoto (Box 10)
    - 1972 Apr. 20-21, Statement on Maintaining Missionary Personnel in Japan, Adopted by the 56th Council of Cooperation General Meeting (Box 10)
    - 1975 June, Educational Evangelism in Japan, Nobuo Kobayashi (Box 10)
    - 1975 June, Misfortune and Death, R.W. Brownlee (Box 10)
    - 1976 Jan. 20, An Appeal from a Hiroshima A-Bomb Survivor, Shinichi Kato (Box 10)
    - [1976?], Message from the scroll presented to Mary McMillan on the occasion of the 90th anniversary of Hiroshima Jo Gakuin (Box 10)
    - Hiroshima Union Church sermon by Doris Hartman, 1978 Feb. 26 (Box 10)
    - 1980 May 29, Searching, Dorothy A. Stroup (Box 10)
    - 1981 Feb. 12, Moments with Mary become Special Memories, Melody Kirchner (Box 10)
    - 1981 Aug. 9, I Take Hiroshima Personally, Patricia J. Patterson (Box 10)
    - 1982 Jan. 20, Confessions of Responsibility during World War II, revised English translation (Box 10)
    - 1982 June 24, Statement by Takeshi Araki, Mayor of Hiroshima on the Occasion of the Second Special Session of the United Nations General Assembly Devoted to Disarmament (Box 10)
    - 1988 Aug. 12, An Echo from Hiroshima, Jane McMillan Greenwood (Box 10)
    - 1989 Nov. 10, Lawrance Thompson Memorial Service (Box 10)
    - 1991 July 24,Eulogy delivered by Mitsuko Iguchi at the memorial service for Mary McMillan (Box 10)
    - 1991 July 24, The Service of Resurrection for Mary Connely McMillan (Box 10)
    - 1992-1993 Winter, The Story of Sadako, no author (Box 10)
    - undated, Atomic Bomb Casualties in Hiroshima (II): Physical Effects of the Atomic Bomb in Hiroshima, Hiroshima Atomic Bomb Casualty Research Group (Box 10)
    - undated, Christians and Peace, Maurine Parker (Box 10)
    - undated, Cora Julia Harrison, no author (Box 10)
    - undated, Food resource quiz, no author (Box 10)
    - undated, F.O.R. Policy Statement on Indochina by the Fellowship of Reconciliation (Box 10)
    - undated, He Set his Face Steadfastly, Anna Bell Williams (Box 10)
    - undated, In the Autumn Wind by Dorothy Stroup: Review of Novel, no author (Box 10)
    - undated, Jonah, no author (Box 10)
    - undated, The Kyodan of Tomorrow, Masahisa Suzuki (Box 10)
    - undated, Missionary Relationships in my Kyodu, no author (Box 10)
    - undated, Mary, Sue Severn (Box 10)
    - undated, My Life in Hiroshima, Doris Hartman (Box 10)
    - undated, Negotiation Now, a Petition Circulated by Vietnam Summer Japan, a New Group in Tokyo and Hiroshima, Concerned About the War in Vietnam (Box 10)
    - undated, Peace, Joan Woodward (Box 10)
    - undated, A Poem, no author (Box 10)
    - undated, A Précis of the Main Points of Sister Carolyn Jean?s Talk, no author (Box 10)
    - undated, Questions for the Article on what Christian Organizations, Institutions, and Individuals in Hiroshima are Doing for Disarmament and Peace, no author (Box 10)
    - undated, Report of Survey Deputation to Evaluate the Relief Needs of Atomic Bomb Victims, no author (Box 10)
    - undated, Some High Points in the Life of Mary McMillan, written by teachers and students at Hiroshima Jo Gakuin College (Box 10)
    - undated, A Sorrowful Tale of Elephants, Yukio Tsuchiya (Box 10)
    - undated, Tribute, Shiro Abe (Box 10)
    - undated, Witness for Shalom, no author (Box 10)
  - Audiovisual Material Subseries, 1979-1990 and undated
    Videotapes, audio cassettes, and one phonograph record containing recordings of speeches and debates regarding the future of Japan, the history of Hiroshima Jo Gakuin College, and the continued effects in Hiroshima of the atomic bomb. Also included is a video of McMillan's farewell ceremony prior to her retirement, as well as an LP recording of the song A Message for Tomorrow. Arranged in original order. Use copies are available for the audio cassettes. Master audio cassette tapes are filed immediately following the use copies.
    - 1979, Mary McMillan, Fall 1979, Tape 2, Copy 1 (use copy), audio cassette (Box 10)
    - undated, War and Peace, Lectures by Dr. Sigeaki Hirohara and The Mourning for the Dead by A-Bomb (use copy), audio cassette (Box 10)
    - undated, A-Bomb Survivors Recollect and Try to Express (use copy), audio cassette (Box 10)
    - MASTER copies of previous recordings, 3 audio cassettes (Box 10)
    - 1980 Spring, Mary Departing Japan, BetaMax videotape (Box 10)
    - 1986, 1886-1986: Hiroshima Jo Gakuin College Commemoration, VHS videotape (Box 10)
    - 1990 Aug. 6,A-Bomb Anniversary Programs, VHS videotape (Box 10)
    - 1990 Aug. 25, Excerpts from Debate: Approaching 21st Century, Where?s Japan Heading?, VHS videotape (Box 10)
    - undated, A Message for Tomorrow, made by Hiroshima-Nagasaki Publishing Company, phonograph record (Box 10)
- Photographic Material Series, 1943-1967 and undated
  Divided into two subseries for photographs and for slides; the material is further organized by subject matter. There are images of the Topaz Relocation Center in Utah, Hiroshima Jo Gakuin College, McMillan's friends, former students and their families. Other images document her travels throughout East Asia, including trips to China and Taiwan. The bulk of the material consists of black-and-white and color casual snapshots of McMillan, her Japanese friends, and her former students with their families. These photographs document Japanese wedding traditions and other ceremonies as well as various marches and activities promoting peace and nuclear disarmament. There are ten images taken at the Topaz Japanese internment camp; most of the photographs were labeled with names and sometimes dates. The slides are in color and consist chiefly of images from McMillan's travels. All materials are arranged in chronological order
  - Photographs Subseries, 1943-1965 and undated
    - 1943,Topaz Relocation Center (Box 11)
    - 1947-1965, undated,Hiroshima Jo Gakuin College (Box 11)
    - undated, Former students, their families, and friends (Box 11)
    - undated, Other photographs from Japan (Box 11)
  - Slides Subseries, 1947-1967 and undated
    - 1947, undated,China and Taiwan (Box 11)
    - 1966, undated,Hiroshima (Box 11)
    - 1966-1967, undated,Hiroshima Jo Gakuin College (Box 11)
    - undated, Inland Sea of Seto (Box 11)
    - undated, Japan, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - undated, Rural life in Japan (Box 11)
    - undated, Tea Ceremony (Box 11)
- Scrapbooks Subseries, 1940-1982
  Contains two bound volumes: a guest book kept by McMillan from 1940 to 1982, which lists the names and addresses of her visitors, and a scrapbook of notes and photographs, compiled by the students and staff at Hiroshima Jo Gakuin College and presented to McMillan upon her retirement in 1980.
  - Guest book, 1940-1982 (Box 12)
  - Retirement scrapbook, 1980 (Box 12)
- Printed Material Series, 1936-1997 and undated